so now that we have seen what storage
devices look like let's talk about how
they and other io devices can be
connected to the system we usually
connect io devices using some sort of a
standardized io bus
it needs to have a standard because we
want to be able to connect for example
hard drives from one manufacturer
to a computer built by another one and
then possibly even replace the hard
drive with another one from another
manufacturer or even move our existing
hard drive from one system to a new one
we are buying so that we can access our
data without having to spend a lot of
time copying it because these buses have
standards they have a limited rate of
improvement and often this improvement
goes in steps
so although the technology might go up
in a relatively smooth fashion
this is where a new standard gets
adopted by manufacturers this is another
one and so on meanwhile
this is where a new standard gets
adopted by a manufacturer so things
suddenly improve
but then for a while you just have the
same buses even though the technology is
actually improving
and instead of having just one type of
bus that connects to all i o devices
typically we have a hierarchy of buses
you have a mesoninbus such as pci
express it will be pretty fast and short
so that it can be this fast and it can
be used to directly connect fast devices
to the processor such as for example
graphics
then we will connect storage buses to it
for example the sata
or scasi for hard drives
both of these are used usually to
connect storage devices
these
are somewhat specialized for storage
and a
sata controller
will act
as a pci express device on the mezzanine
bus
but the controller itself actually
controls
a sata bus to which we now connect
devices
so the reason why we have these and
don't directly connect their hard drives
to the pci express
is that although
these
for example serial atta buses are slower
there is also less change in their
standards and there need not be that
much change because these devices
are much slower
than what the pci express can provide so
we don't really need all the speed of
pci express in exchange
we get
to keep our hard drive standards for a
while longer while pci express
can improve a little bit more rapidly
all we have to do
is devise new controllers that connect
these
storage buses to the newest pci express
that we have
and then we can have
a usb hub for example also attached to a
pci express bus
the usb hub itself provides a usb bus
connection for usb devices
that are even slower
than for example sata but
again
their standard lives for a lot longer so
we can use a lot of different devices
relatively cheaply and connect them to
this
so overall what we can have is a pci
express bus to which we can attach the
processor the graphics the io bus
control for disks for usb and these in
turn provide
buses to which we can attach disks here
and all sorts of devices here so the
closer we get to the processor the more
important it is to keep improving speeds
because because some of the devices like
graphics need that speed
but for storage and for many of the
standard usb devices
we really are much more interested in
standardization so that we can exchange
this so that we can interchange these
devices and not have them tied to a
particular technology and have to change
them every year or two